So,
we have determined that we would go
through the two sections from this
famous teaching
uh
that concern meditation and then uh
emptiness.
And uh
we had uh started the meditation section
last weekend. And then I felt like we
should
continue it this weekend rather than
during the week because a lot of people
move home and can work. Uh Scott, you
got
crank up this baby cuz they're going to
get sleepy. Uh
if they're not already.
And so uh
I'm going to be continuing
a discussion of meditation that we began
last weekend.
Uh
maybe by Sunday we'll get to a little
bit of uh
emptiness, continue a little bit of
emptiness, okay?
Mhm.
Today uh in the morning we had a
practice meditation together. We did an
hour together.
I think we did a
20 minutes of talking. Then we did 10 13
minutes of uh
warm-up, meditation warm-up.
Then we did I don't think more than 5
minutes of or 7 minutes of meditation.
And we went deeper and deeper into an
object. And and at by the end everybody
was in deep.
Uh
for a few minutes, just a few minutes,
maybe three four minutes, all right?
And we held it deep, way deep for three
four minutes, and then we just stopped.
And and we talked about it, okay?
That's what uh what we're trying to say
is thunder and nature you want to check
out.
They're all of the me and you, people
like you and me
we hope to have a a very long period of
fixation on the object. We we believe
that we should be capable of sitting in
deep meditation for half an hour or an
hour or something like that. We are
thinking
but
in reality
we only bump into the object once in a
while.
Like during a whole meditation object,
we sort of wandering around and once in
a while it gets in our way and we hit
it.
Uh
but what we are supposed to be
meditating on
Uh
so we are sort of worse than
intermittent meditators. We just hit it
once in a while.
Therefore
there was a custom in Tibet
that rather than doing an hour
and say doing an hour in the morning and
an hour in the afternoon and then an
hour in the evening it was a custom in
Tibet
to divide your waking hours into 18
18 parts, right?
Uh so if you have like I don't know
let's say you have 6 hours of meditation
time
uh you would divide that into 18 parts,
20 minutes a piece
and you would do sessions of 20 minutes
long, okay? If you include there the
preliminaries
and the dedication at the end
you would be on the meditation object
for 5 to 7 minutes, something like that.
So rather than sitting down, especially
those of you doing three year retreat,
you might want to try rather than trying
to do a whole hour on the object or
something which which you won't do.
Uh
divide the day to 18 parts, uh do 20
minute sessions
and try to stay on the object for maybe
5 to 10 minutes, okay? Really stay on
the object.
It's much much better to start with 5
minutes
intensely on the object and slowly build
that up maybe 1 minute a week, okay?
Maybe you increase it 1 minute a week.
Rather than sitting for an hour and
wandering around. If you sit for an hour
and wander around, you will never
improve in your meditation. And you get
into a very very uh addictive bad habit.
And you you won't even notice you have
it. You will just your meditation will
be dull
and and you will never know. You'll just
spend an hour wandering around. You will
never taste real meditation. You will
never get the high
visions and and personal experiences
that result from meditation. And then
sooner or later you'll just quit
uh because nothing will be happening,
all right? So, rather, see if you can
stay on the object for 5 good minutes.
Do a nice long preliminary.
Uh do some breath meditation.
Go to the object for 5 minutes.
Come off the object. Do a Thanksgiving
meditation. Think about all the people
in your life who've helped you,
the kindness of all the people around
you.
Dedicate the good karma to someone else.
20 minutes, stop.
And then go for another 20 minutes later
in the day. Don't do this 1 hour thing
or even a half hour thing.
You will be off the object
and you will get used to that. And it
it'll be very hard to change later, you
know?
Uh I I teach a lot of people Tibetan
and the the very best thing is if they
don't have any Tibetan before
because their pronunciation is always
wrong
and they they they know a lot of strange
things and I'd rather have someone who
doesn't know anything.
Uh it's much easier to start with a
person like that. So,
let's not don't get into any bad habits.
20 minutes.
Start with 20 minutes. Even those of you
who think you can meditate. I mean,
today I think we felt some deep
meditation in the room
for 2 minutes.
When we were on the grains of sand, for
2 minutes we had deep meditation going
in the room. And that's that's good.
Then you increase it from there.
Uh to to machine gun
If you do short sessions, you will be
able to avoid the great the two great
obstacles to meditation which are
getting dull
just a dull feeling, dullness, and
restlessness, thinking about lunch,
okay?
Uh Buddha you will reach a kind of
meditation for 4 5 minutes which is free
of those two extremes.
Therefore,
two new Dharma say two new
Short sessions, lots of sessions,
all right? Two is a is a saying.
Short sessions, lots of sessions.
Two new Dharma, okay?
If you keep up the principle of many
short
sessions, 20 minute sessions,
Buddha talking means automatically
without noticing it
your your fixation on the object will
start to get longer. The
the time on the object will get longer
by itself. You don't have to fight for
it. All right,
they don't say
you and sing.
And then you can start to increase the
length of your meditation sessions,
okay? You'll know
uh because you'll be on the on the
object more,
young man good chain any apaya.
Nyan mong amang Cittavisa any apaya.
Cittavisa.
He's going on to the final of the five
classical problems of meditation. What
were the five classical problems of
meditation? Number one was called
Nyan mong.
Which means I don't feel like meditating
today. I think I'll skip today.
I I'm not giving up my meditation
practice. I'm devoted to my meditation
practice. I want to get enlightened.
I appreciate that it's necessary to save
all living beings.
But I have a pretty hard day coming up
and I think I'll just skip it. I don't
feel like it.
Today.
That's meditation problem number one. If
you have meditation problem number one,
it's kind of a good thing cuz you'll
never get
the other four.
Nyan mong is number one. Number two is
amang Cittavisa.
Forgetting the instructions, which is a
code word in meditation circles for
losing the losing you lose the object of
thinking. You're off the object of
thinking.
Normally in the beginning you're not
even aware you're off the object. You're
thinking about lunch.
And then there's this mental, you know,
jolt like two minutes later you're like,
"Ah, hey, I lost the object like two
minutes ago.
You know, I've been thinking about lunch
for like two minutes.
And I didn't even notice. Okay, that's
the second meditation problem. So what
was the third meditation problem? Nyan
mong amang Cittavisa. Yeah, you get on
the object, okay? You're
you're able to get on the object. The
minute you're on the object you will
have one of two problems. You will start
to get unclear. The mind's power, the
mind's clarity, the mind's freshness
will drop slightly.
Or you'll start to get restless and your
mind will want to break off the object.
So
uh
the the number three is really the main
meditation challenge. And that's where
you will spend 90% of your meditation
life, okay? If you get past number one.
Uh,
and
and you're correcting between the two,
right? Uh, what's meditation problem
number four?
Problem four.
Yeah, you don't correct. You catch your
mind is not fresh. You catch that your
mind has no intensity on the object. You
do not feel like a person listening to
their breath, right? And you know it.
And you don't do anything about it,
right? Uh, your mind is down. Or else,
you're
you're not distracted to dinner yet, but
you feel restless down deep. You don't
You don't feel calm and focused on the
object. You You feel like you're about
to think of something else, right?
Uh, go to trouble.
Uh, subtle subtle restlessness, right?
So,
when those two things happen, you must
take take action. You must correct.
And the the fourth problem of meditation
is not to take action when you should
have taken action.
Think of action as the constant
correction of a person driving a car,
okay? The hands never really stop.
They're constantly going like this and
then they're going like that. A good
driver
uh,
a bad driver is, you know, a new driver
is
is correcting to the left and then they
go to far and then there's a jerk and
they they correct that, right? And then
a an experienced driver they can talk on
their cell phone and and
you know, they can text texting.
Uh,
but their hand is is moving all the
time. They're like slight corrections. A
meditator
at stage number four is
is correcting constantly and they're not
totally even aware of it. The mind gets
a little down, they they spice it up.
The mind is too spiced up, they bring it
down a little bit. And it's a constant
It doesn't stop for a long, long time.
You will be there for a long, long time
where you going to have to do constant
corrections and time for. So, don't feel
bad, all right? You will You are then
you come back, then you go back, then
you come back. You come back too much,
you go forward. You go too much, you
come back. You keep overcorrecting.
There comes a time when you reach a
balance a total balance, okay?
Uh you don't do samapatti in Sanskrit.
Uh
The mind is completely balanced. There's
no dullness
and there's no restlessness. The mind is
running uh a middle way
very, very smooth, very, very natural.
The corrective process has become so
fine
that there's not even any tiny
adjustments going on. The mind is
flowing perfectly down the middle of the
two
other states of mind, right?
What do you think would be a problem
then?
State of mind.
Yeah.
Don't fix it if it ain't broke.
That was a saying in my company in in
the factory. We had a factory big
factory.
There was a saying, you know, don't
don't fix it if it ain't broke. Like if
it's flowing
stay stay away. Let the mind flow. If
the mind is flowing nicely
let leave it alone. Let it flow, all
right? Then it would be a problem if you
try to tighten up or loosen up or
something
means
uh ting na nyom ma wang ma du che pa
nyen nyen. It would be a problem of
meditation if you attempted to apply a
counter
antidote to a problem that wasn't there
at the moment, right?
Then nyen ma du che che gi ge wa, du me
che wa dam nyom then good day.
The fix for problem number five is
antidote number eight, which is
Leave it alone. Okay.
Don't take any action. Okay?
Antidote number four is
Do something. Antidote number five is
Don't do anything.
Leave it alone.
The meditation is rolling, leave it
alone.
Don't worry, you won't get there for a
long time. You are
You will not have a period
in your meditation career which is not
plagued by
uh dullness and restlessness until you
reach the eighth level. Right, there are
nine levels of meditation.
Uh until you reach level number eight
uh
you won't experience any uh you know,
relief from these two states. You will
constantly be going like this.
There won't be a time when you don't
have restlessness or
dullness to fight. Okay?
At the eighth level
uh
your restlessness
and your dullness have been have been
subdued. All right?
If If when you have overcome those two
things, you keep looking for them. All
right? Checking for them.
And you basically
and you take some kind of If you make
some kind of effort to fix something
it will disturb your meditation.
So, to generally you have to keep a
watch dog mind, right? It's called
shishin.
One corner of your mind has to be
watching the rest of your mind. Not all
the time, okay? It's checking in from
time to time to see if you left the
object 2 minutes ago or 10 minutes ago
or an hour ago, okay?
Like there's a part of your mind which
is watching. When you reach meditation
level eight, you call off the watch dog.
You say, "Okay, you rest for a while.
We don't have any problems here." Now,
you you check in too often would become
a problem. So, you just cool chill for a
while.
Okay? You're telling your watch dog mind
to chill for a while. If you start
watching when I don't have any problems,
I'll have to watch for you, okay?
Shishin sum up in there.
But,
look at chocolate. We take down your
test. Um
This is a thing This is a thing called
uh it's a it's a thing called
neutrality, okay? Uh um that means
neutrality.
It's similar to the word upekkha in the
yoga sutra.
Uh
But, that upekkha means don't see some
people as friends and some people as
enemies. Learn to treat everyone
equally.
Uh so, there are three kinds of upekkha.
One is uh in the practice of love, in
learning to love,
we try to reach a state where we treat
people equally. Equanimity in the sense
of equally.
Then, there's an upekkha
upekkha
which refers to karmic content.
And it means this action is neither
karmically
uh
virtuous nor karmically non-virtuous.
It's It's upekkha. It's somewhere
between. It's neutral, okay? Like
sleeping
is considered a neutral mental function.
Anger is a
bad karmic mental function. Uh
compassion is a good kind of mental
function. Sleep normally is
is a picture. It's neither It's neither.
The third sense of a picture is
scripture is is this one here. It means
leave it alone. Don't mess with it.
Don't know means leave it.
Okay. Don't know means chill.
Shay shay is the word for that, but
lumpa chopa. At this point, you are
allowed to chopa means you are allowed
to to relax.
Only at level eight, you are allowed to
chill.
Relax. Lumpa means let it go.
Relax. Okay? Just
What do you call it? Like let it go.
It's a very famous word. Lumpa means
chill.
All right. Let it go. Let go of the
watch mind watch dog mind, which is the
first level at which you do that. Not
until level eight do you do you let up
on your watch dog mind lookout mind.
Okay?
Great masters of the past from India and
Tibet
and China who were great meditators
they all recognized that there was a
point
called the eighth level of meditation
where
because you were no longer in danger of
falling into dullness or restlessness,
it was appropriate to let up on your
watch dog mind. Okay? For the first time
in your whole meditation career, when
you hit level eight, you can you can
tell him to just calm down, okay? You
don't have to do anything. You can take
a rest.
We don't need you to check whether we
have dullness or restlessness cuz we're
we're up to level eight, nine, and we're
not going to get them anyway. In fact,
if you intervene, we'll it will have to
cause a problem, okay?
But, until such time as you reach the
eighth level
uh cut schedule on the other seven
levels
you have chamber, right? The the mind
tied to the object,
okay? Awareness of the object. The mind
is physically wrote to the object,
chamber.
What's na?
Na is like intensity, the intensity.
The intensity of your mind into your
favorite song.
The the few lines of your favorite song
that you like the best.
Come through in the stand.
It's the beginning of the instrumental.
And your mind is it sinks into that
those notes, okay? That's na,
okay?
In the middle of your favorite the
favorite page of your favorite book of
all time.
Na.
Men means we aren't saying that you
should release
your na, and we aren't saying that you
should release the rope on the object
before the eighth level, na,
okay?
Don't you can't release those before the
eighth level, okay?
Say lura.
Lura.
Gora.
This was an old famous
meditators axiom. What do you call
idiom?
Cliché.
Saying.
In the old days. Let it go means
I got to get it. I just got to get a
catchy English thing.
Let go. I'm not going to Okay, let go
find meditate fine. Okay, let go find
meditate.
That doesn't work, right?
Heart meditation is heart letting go.
Something like that. I don't know.
There was a saying that the best
meditation was when you let go.
I don't know. Meditation is letting go.
Meditation is letting go.
So, that came to be a
People who had reached level eight
started to say to each other, "Hey, the
best meditation is when you let go,
right?"
Other people who hadn't reached the
eighth level heard that.
They told the watchdog to go to sleep at
level six.
And then they spent all day thinking
about breakfast or lunch. Do you see
what I mean? Okay, they let go too
early. Okay.
And it became a problem. So, none of us
did that.
They failed to recognize the proper
line at which you could let go. Okay.
Uh
quality of your mind.
Your mind.
If you let go of your awareness before
the eighth level, that's a mistake.
Check. Then Jason and Ronald. So, don't
get misled if you run into that saying
somewhere. Okay.
They teach you Why is that? Nature of
your mind. Chemo trauma shown it.
Things in nature you have
to learn.
Nature of your mind. Chemo trauma shown
it.
It is true, he says.
If you get some kind of sense of
surrender
before the eighth level, where you're
kind of letting go, you might be able to
You might be able
quick progress on fixation. Okay? The
fixation part, you will make some quick
progress if you let go even a little
earlier than you should.
But, the fixation part will go well.
But,
uh chigwan tramo shor,
you will fall into subtle dullness.
Okay? What was subtle dullness?
It was kind of like spacing out on the
object. Okay? You don't lose the object.
And you don't even lose, uh some sort of
freshness of the mind, but there's no
intensity on the object.
It's listening to your favorite song in
a dentist's office.
Okay? I do that.
I spend a lot of time there. He plays,
you know,
70s and 80s hits.
Cuz we're about the same age. And, uh
you know, I'm
I don't lose the music, and my mind is,
you know, aware
cuz he's drilling.
And, uh
but I'm not really, uh so I haven't lost
myself in the music exactly cuz he's got
his hand in my mouth.
Okay?
So, there's no mind. Okay? That's subtle
dullness. I'm aware of the music, and
I'm into I
To some extent, I'm I'm enjoying my
favorite songs,
but there's definitely not this deep
pleasure in the song at that moment,
right?
Uh mind means
intensity.
Shor means So, if you rush things too
quickly about letting go,
you know, not making effort.
If you drop the effort too early,
uh you may speed up your fixation, speed
up your frustration, but you won't have
any You won't fall into the object. You
won't get lost in the object, okay?
And then the whole process will be
delayed.
The progress of your meditation will be
delayed, okay?
It's very interesting. He said all of
these
descriptions about how to meditate
follow for all spiritual
uh
steps that you would For every spiritual
goal that you might have,
the process is the same. All the way
from the first day you heard a Buddhist
teaching up until the day that you are
practicing the highest forms of tantra,
uh the process of how to concentrate is
the same.
The process for how to hold the object
is the same.
These nine levels apply to every stage
of practice from the first day you begin
up to the day you become enlightened.
They They don't change.
So, let's talk about diamond council
shamatha means Okay, so let's talk in
practical terms. How you going to do
your meditation now? So, you now you
know the nine levels, you know the five
problems, you know the eight antidotes.
Uh then kind of let's get more into the
nitty-gritty about how you're actually
going to do this, okay?
You are going to seek a place which has
the five qualities which we discussed.
Good place, good friends,
doesn't make you sick, you can get stuff
you need easily. You have your training
wheel.
She makes all the stuff you need.
Get all these prerequisites ready.
Uh
then there were Nam Nam Chung Dong Gyai
Dor.
Sit on your meditation cushion in a
seven part
uh
posture of Vairocana. Okay? So,
Vairocana is a
is a high uh tantric angel.
And
uh there's a meditation posture which is
named after uh Vairocana. And it has
either seven or eight uh components
depending on how you count them. I'm
going to give you a traditional uh
presentation of the medicine.
Because he doesn't. All right? So,
here's the
traditional way of teaching them.
Uh seven parts to a correct meditation
posture. Number one,
uh it's called your legs, okay? Uh
refers to your legs. Your legs should be
in a comfortable position
which will not cause you pain for the
length of your meditation, okay? It
doesn't matter if you're sitting in a
chair.
Uh you can have your back against the
wall and extend your legs. You can do uh
half lotus.
Vajra can do. You can do a full lotus.
Uh then you can do you can do sukhasana.
You can just have the legs
crossed but but not on top of each
other. You can do any uh variation. You
can sit in virasana with your with your
heels under your bottom or off to the
side. Uh it doesn't siddhasana is good.
You you you put one heel strongly into
the groin and then another heel under
that. You might experiment with that.
Try it out. It's kind of fun.
Uh
And and these are different meditation
postures you can take. It doesn't matter
which one you take. Park your legs.
Park your legs.
Nobody's watching you,
okay? Except the Buddhas of the
universe.
Uh,
they don't care what you look like. They
don't care if you're sitting in a full
lotus. If you're sitting in a full lotus
and concentrating on the pain in your
knees, you that's the most foolish thing
you can do. You're a fool. You should be
sitting in a position where you can
forget about your body. You won't
nothing will
no part of your body will be calling up
your mind and saying, "We hurt down
here."
Okay?
You want to sit in a way that's
neutral, right? You don't want the body
talking at all. You don't want to
park your body. Sit on a couch like
lounging around. I don't care.
Generally speaking, it's good well,
we'll get there. So, number two, the
eyes, okay?
Number two is the eyes. The eyes can be
closed completely,
but there's a slight danger that you
might get sleepy because the only time
you close your eyes normally is when
you're about to go to sleep. So, you
know, 30, 40, 50 years of habituation
will kick in. Close your eyes and get
drowsy right away.
So, there's a tradition
which is very cool. You might want to
try it, okay? You
eyes half open.
And then, uh,
it's very important that the chin is
still parallel to the floor, right? But
the eyes are gazing down, right?
And, uh,
let the eyelids just droop, okay?
Which also is a test of whether you're
feeling
calm or not.
Like in yoga, if your eyes are eyelids
are tight and your jaw's tight here, it
means you're
you haven't relaxed into the pose.
You're still fighting the pose, right?
So,
like this, and then your eyes are like
this. Then the the classical texts say,
"Stare at your nose." So, there have
been hundreds of years of people making
the mistake of
And what stare at your nose means
relax the eyes into a thirsty, right?
Into a gaze, which is neutral in the
area of right here, the plane of your
nose, okay?
So,
don't focus your eyes on on any object
in front of the eyes. Let them be Let
them hang unfocused in the area of the
plane of your nose.
So, you don't have to cross your eyes.
It's just like this, okay? But, the
tendency is to drop the whole head,
right?
So, keep the head up, but let the eyes
down. And then, let the eye eyelids go
as as far as they normally go.
And there will be a little slit here,
and that will keep you awake,
okay? But, the amount of light
that comes into the eyes
when they are when the eyelids are
drooped,
is is will keep you from getting sleepy,
right?
Personally, I've found They don't say it
in the text, but uh
I had a lot of trouble I had a paisley
altar cloth,
and uh
you know, I would start
looking at the designs, you know? And
what I found in my own practice is that
if the whole area right in front of your
face is neutral, like a an altar cloth
with a solid color,
uh it's better, okay? So, put a some
kind of a cloth that there's no texture
to it, and there's no outline there's no
designs to it.
It's better even than looking at table
legs or something, cuz then you'll start
to
you know, uh
So, it's like that, and then your eyes
are are droopy.
And they're just looking down, but don't
let your chin fall. All right? Okay,
that's number two. Number three.
Uh
Kemet Sigma should be like a septum.
It means uh your spine should be like a
stack of golden coins. Like the
vertebrae should be stacked nicely on
each one. In reality, we know there are
natural curves in the spine.
In the actual practice, it's the
Alexander
technique.
Kinesthetic misapprehension. You feel
like it's straight.
It feels like each one is stacked on the
other, okay? And that's It should feel
like it's
It should feel like each vertebra is is
stacked on the other one. Uh
Equal pressure on the vertebra
brain all the way up the spine.
It means a straight back. Like if many
great Tibetan masters have said that the
key to good meditation is a straight
back. And I think that thing about tying
a string to the top of your head and
imagine somebody's pulling it up, that
can be very useful.
Uh a clue here uh or suggestion
that actually I heard a couple from
different people, but one's from a
Master Leon
in Vancouver. He's a
Wushu master.
What do you call it?
Tai chi chi kung master. But he
he said, "Be careful about
Be careful about uh
crooking your lower back in. Don't don't
make a notch in your lower back." He
And they say that, you know, some good
yoga teachers say that. Uh what do you
call it? Tuck the tailbone.
You know, you The tendency when you
think you're sitting up straight will be
to make a dent in the lower back and
stick your butt out, and that actually
chokes the prana slightly.
It slightly hurts the prana. So,
is that
this guy nicely and I am going I guess.
So, you you tuck the tailbone slightly
and you lengthen the the very base of
the spine.
Just above the tailbone, all right?
So, like that. That's a straight back
and not and not like that, you know?
Okay.
The shoulders should be equal, okay? I
tend to go like this.
And try to get the shoulders
down equal,
Shoulders on the back, right?
The head should be uh
should be the chin should be parallel to
the floor.
They say in the scriptures that if you
tilt the head back too far,
you will get uh good luck, right? You
will get uh
restlessness. The mind will become
restless.
Uh chin if you tilt the head forward,
you will get chi up.
You will get uh dullness, okay? So,
restlessness,
dullness.
And you you want keep the head erect on
the neck,
long neck,
uh head up,
and uh level, and not going up, not
going down. Then you know friends of you
might take a lot of people you peek at
them.
They'll they're they're going like this,
you know what I mean?
They're going like this.
Uh
The teeth should be not clenched, okay?
The teeth should be
uh relaxed. They say ramso char, it
means leave the teeth the way they
normally are. Don't clench them.
Don't do anything. However, your teeth
fall naturally, let them fall freely.
Uh and then the tongue check
should
There's a trick and you can experiment
with it, okay?
When you touch the tip of the tongue,
the top of the tip of the tongue
to the
palate just behind the
teeth, okay? And that keeps your mouth
from getting dry.
Don't press it tightly, but
uh
let it park there. Park your tongue.
Uh
slightly touching the top of your mouth,
okay?
This is the traditional posture for
meditation, which has been taught for
thousands of years. This is the posture
of Vairocana, okay?
Sometimes an eighth
element is added to traditionally to the
seven-point posture, and that's watching
your breath, okay?
In this tradition, watching your breath
uh
was first described in the
Abhidharmakośa around 350 AD by
Vasubandhu.
Uh
and he had a chapter in on meditation,
and I think it's the sixth sixth
chapter.
But he describes uh Ujjayi the breath
meditation,
which was at the time it was only used
for
I I like to call it putting the car in
neutral, okay? Like if you have a 1980
Volvo station wagon, especially,
uh
you have to put the brakes on. You go in
reverse, you you pull out of the post
office,
out of the parking lot, and you out of
the parking space, and you go to
reverse, right? And you
you're back, and then you don't like jam
it right into first and take off, you
know? Cuz the Volvo doesn't like that.
You know, you have to stop,
pause,
chew some gum,
uh
put it in neutral, wait for a while, and
then you can take both hands off.
You can put it into first, all right?
The car should be stopped, you see? The
practice of watching your breath
was meant to be a segue
between,
you know,
get the busyness of getting up and
brushing your teeth and having your
favorite herbal tea
and starting your meditation. It was
meant to be a segue into meditation. It
was never meant to be a meditation in
itself.
Uh
then in some countries the whole
Buddhist teachings didn't get there.
In In Burma, Thailand, Ceylon,
uh
Vietnam,
Three of the great subjects didn't make
it there. They only got Vinaya and
Abhidharma
in those countries. And then so they got
Abhidharma, somebody went crazy on the
breath thing,
and now they just watch the breath all
day.
Uh
It's a nice thing to watch your breath,
and it it puts the mind into neutral.
But then But then you should pick an
important object.
You know, then you should pick some kind
of object which is karmically powerful.
Uh like your lama's image or like your
like emptiness or like compassion.
You know, you should
put the car into first, you know, don't
just sit there in neutral all day.
Okay, like that.
What was I talking about? Oh, yeah. So,
counting the breath
is considered the eighth
part of a proper posture. You count the
breath for a minute or 2 minutes, and
then you start your meditation, all
right? Okay.
Those are the non non chigye or non non
chigye.
or my shot.
So, there was a custom, one of the
meditations you might want to try
is to picture your teacher
or any other enlightened being that you
honor
on the top of your head facing the same
way, okay?
And they say uh tsung k'ang. Tsung k'ang
means uh
the distance from your thumb joint to
the tip of your thumb,
okay? Like that big.
You picture a llama
uh your teacher or or you picture any
holy being at the top of your head
facing the same way.
You can uh
then you can split off another one and
bring it down to the level of your
navel, all right?
Then then they would take it by the
right shoulder and leave it facing your
at the level of your navel facing up,
all right? Padmasambhava.
They are the moon name of Samantabhadra
and Jñānaśūnyatā.
Uh Jigten Migur
By the way, there's a reason to put it
uh a visualization in front of your
navel chakra or in front of your heart
chakra or in front of your throat
chakra. There's a There's a special way
in in Buddhism you you
you ring your bell and you you ring your
drum, right?
And then you're supposed to ring the
bell in front of your heart chakra and
you're supposed to ring the drum in
front of your navel chakra. And that
stimulates those chakras.
Uh same with visualizing objects before
those in front of those chakras, okay?
Uh Minling Dorje Sempa and Jñānaśūnyatā
Jigten Migur, uh they are the moon name
of Samantabhadra and Jñānaśūnyatā.
You will not
have a clear picture of the object from
the first day that you try,
Jigten Migur, and you don't have to
worry about it, he says. That's natural.
This is nice. This is really nice.
There's different ways to meditate,
which we'll go into, right?
Say jowo.
chego
What's the other one? shawu shawu
jowo
chego
shawu
Now, that's three totally different
types of meditation.
Jowo is where you you put your mind on a
single object and hold it there. Like
you try to picture your lama.
Or you try to meditate on emptiness
without thinking about anything else,
okay? That's jowo. Jowo means set the
set the mind on that object. Jowo Jowo
means set it. Jowo means meditate.
Chego means problem-solving meditation,
okay?
Someone's bothering you at work, all
right? And you can't
You can't
get it off your mind. You you can't get
over it,
right?
So, you have to do a chego, you know?
This person's always criticizing me.
Then you say, "Okay.
So, where did they come from?"
Well,
you know, like everything else, it comes
from me.
Well, why do you think they're
criticizing you? You know, you ask
yourself questions
in meditation. Well, I guess I must have
criticized somebody in the past. Well,
have you criticized anybody in the last
week? Well, yeah, you know, I guess I
have. A couple days ago, I was said
something to so-and-so.
Uh
do you think you could Do you really
want to get rid of this person that's
criticizing you? Yes.
Uh
so, why don't you just remove the seed
from your mind? Okay, how would you do
that? Well, I guess I would
go after the seed by refusing to
criticize this criticizable person.
Uh
Well, when do you plan to do this?
I guess I can start tomorrow. Yeah,
well, where and what time?
You know, and this is a jiggle. This is
a jiggle. This is a
uh analytical meditation.
And you need it, you know? You need to
analyze the people you don't like
during meditation. Don't go off the
subject and start analyzing why you hate
them.
You will.
You're supposed to be analyzing why you
caused that.
But generally it before it
There's another word.
It changes generation to
into a listing of their faults.
Uh
which would be a short one.
Which is the third kind of meditation.
Third kind of meditation is where you're
I like to think of it as building a new
synapse in your mind.
Like uh I was reading a book about how
the I don't know
the the What was it? The parts of the
mind? Neurons or something.
And they tend to create synapses
at an incredible rate. Like one discrete
thought takes several thousand synaptic
connections.
Uh
but uh
you're trying to build new uh thought
patterns in your mind. You're trying to
purposely construct new bridges of
thought in your mind over which you will
continually travel in the future. All
right? So, for example,
a bad struggle would be where you over
and over you think of all the reasons
why you don't like somebody, you know?
They make me nervous. I walk into the
room. I don't like them. They're always
bugging me. They're always too close to
me, you know? And you
you go over the same
five reasons why you don't like these
people over and over until it becomes a
pattern in your thinking. Us, you know,
it becomes a solid structure in your
mental
uh building. And And then it's really
hard to break. What we seem to do in
Buddhist practice is do the opposite.
You know, like what are five reasons why
I should be patient with the people who
bother me at work, you know?
And then you go through these five. What
are the five problems of meditation?
What are the eight antidotes to those
problems? And you purposely review It's
called review meditation. You purposely
review You sit down very artificially
and review the five problems of
meditation 10 times.
You can say it to your own mind.
We're going to go through the five Can
you list
10 times in a row quickly the five
problems of meditation? And then it gets
really firm. Anything done at the core
of the mind
during meditation sticks with you.
Anything done at the core of the mind uh
sticks with you, okay? Any Any review
meditation you do during deep
meditation, it sticks with you. Scott,
you're going to have ready Xeroxes and
you're going to have ready
will, okay? My
Um
Okay.
Um Duke Kalu Rinpoche
Go down Trakshas of Trakshas teachings.
So, we're talking about shamatha here,
fixation, a fixed meditation.
And he says,
"At the beginning, if you're going to
visualize a holy being, just try to get
a a round thing with five sticks on it.
You know, two arms, two legs, and a
head. You know, just try to get a blob
with a smaller blob and four things
coming out.
You know,
cuz you that's all you really honestly
will get. You know?
Try to get the outline of a person.
Sometimes I do a silhouette.
It's very, very powerful if you want to
learn to visualize
a person, start with a silhouette.
Imagine there's a sheet in front of them
and someone is projecting a powerful
light behind them and all you do is all
you can see is their silhouette. And
just work on the silhouette, okay?
Uh
most people don't learn to visualize
very well, all right? They they get
lazy.
They
don't try to visualize the whole thing
at once. You know, I I often just do the
eyes.
Just the eyes staring at me. Two eyes
sitting there and staring at me, you
know?
When I was a kid, they told a story
about this little ghost called Two Eyes.
And uh this farmer would wake up every
night and have to meet this ghost.
Two eyes just staring at him at the foot
of the bed. Like he would wake up and
look down
at the foot of the bed and there were
two eyes staring at him. And it drove
him crazy. He finally got a shotgun
and he went to bed with the shotgun. And
he woke up and two eyes were staring.
And he he shot Two Eyes and he blew his
toes off.
And
so anyways, um
I'm just hoping you won't forget the Two
Eyes thing.
Uh
so, it's just two eyes
uh staring at you, okay? And go into
their You know how like when you're
mushy or you met somebody new and you're
mushy and
you both had some wine and you're like
staring into each other's eyes. So, like
that with your
teacher. You know, if you're going to
meditate on the Buddha or Jesus or
whoever, then just like you're falling
into their eyes. Just do the eyes.
So, at the beginning, don't try to do
the whole thing. Just do the eyes, all
Uh
start with a middle top of our thumb,
see top of the middle. Or you just
forget the blob of the space and just
have a golden light.
Just a golden orb.
You know, this is my holy number.
Just shining. It's like an egg
egg-shaped shining thing. Start with
just a blob of light.
And then later start
adding detail, right?
Then I turn my mind to my jet fighter.
Uh then I turn my mind to my cell phone
and my young black cat.
And just practice holding on to the
silhouette
without letting go. Tie the mind to the
silhouette.
Don't lose the silhouette. You don't
even have to try to improve the
silhouette, right? Just
silhouette, but don't let go of the
silhouette. Tie the mind to the
silhouette. For how long?
Lucky if you can get 5 minutes. Don't
try more because you'll get a bad habit.
Okay?
Don't try more. Okay, once go back
again, do another meditation in 10
minutes.
You can do lots of little tiny ones.
Don't sit there on an object for more
than 5 minutes, you'll get a bad habit.
You won't be strong. You won't be
strong. Stop, take a rest, have a sip of
tea, go back in. Like that, okay?
I turn my mind to my young black cat.
Then I turn my mind to my cheap Corolla.
Then
I turn my mind to my cheap Corolla. Then
I turn my mind to my cheap Corolla.
Uh if you practice
on a simple silhouette
holding the mind to the silhouette, you
can use that practice to explore the two
states of dullness and restlessness. You
can
all the meditation instructions you need
are complete in a single silhouette. You
don't have to go into emptiness or body
tingle or all that.
With a single silhouette, you can
explore the five problems of meditation
and you can master them without getting
the artists.
Okay, just a silhouette, okay?
This is the incomparable
deep advice of the great meditators of
the past,
so get fancy.
Just take a basic object
and and do 5-minute stretches on it.
The the the length will come. The the
the What do you call it?
They call single inter-pair. The
the duration will increase naturally as
you go. Stick with 4-5 minutes at the
beginning, only object, okay? The
duration will come.
And that's enough. A simple object.
Don't get all fancy,
okay? That's just another kind of
restlessness, all right?
They are
If you get
He's kind of wrapping up, okay, before
he moves on to another subject.
If you get dullness, tighten down on
Jintam means tighten down on
tighten down on how you grasp to the
object. Tighten down on the bonding to
the object, okay? Bottom closer to the
object.
Okay, if you feel dullness
If you get restlessness, try to stop any
uh distraction of the mind, okay? Try to
stop the
the mind leaving the object, okay?
away.
Uh if you get pretty good at your
meditation
and you reach a state of fixation,
automatically dullness will start to
come.
There's a joke in Tibet, you know?
You don't get dullness if you have no
fixation.
All right?
Like if you can't stay on the object for
more than 30 seconds, you'll never get
dullness on the object, okay? Cuz you're
not on the object.
You hear the song away? Chingsum chine
selcha tab.
At that point, when you first learn to
hold the object,
you're going to automatically start to
lose the freshness of your mind, okay?
The freshness
of the intense, okay? It's automatic.
Then then chingsum chine means you got
to Then that time, beware of dullness.
Chingsum chine means beware of dullness,
okay?
Watch out for dullness.
Chine selcha tab sing dong dong ding
dong ding dong.
Try to crank up the freshness of the
mind.
Try to crank up the brad pushi tel
nature of the mind, which in Tibetan is
called
clarity.
Like increase the clarity.
Remember that clarity never refers to
the clarity of the
object. It refers to the brightness of
the mind, the fresh fresh feeling of the
mind, okay?
Crank up your clarity, meaning your
freshness, and then
tighten slightly on the object. Tighten
slightly. He compared
tightness on the object to what? Do you
remember?
Holding a cup, right? And if it's too
tight, it'll slip out of your hands,
right? Like a ball. If it's too tight,
it'll slip out of your hands. If it's
not tight enough, you'll spill hot tea
on your arm, right?
And and every human being, you know, by
the time they're four or five, they
learn to
they learn the right amount. They learn
the tight
They learn the proper amount of
tightness. Not too loose, burn your arm.
Not too tight, the ball pops out. Okay?
And And they have to restart with your
meditation. The right
uh degree of tightness and looseness at
the same time. It's that thing in yoga,
you know, be
What do you call it? Like
concentrate, but light up. Something
like that.
Hang on tight.
Hang on loosely.
Hang on Hang on tight and hang on
loosely.
I see.
If your uh fixation
gets too good, right? I'm sorry.
If your clarity gets If the mind gets
too fresh, well, then you're
Restlessness.
Yeah, restlessness. You start to get You
start to think about other things.
Uh then you're Then Then you have to
watch out for restlessness.
Right?
So, what he's describing is
is this process of of driving, okay? You
will be too tight,
light up. You will be too light, tighten
up.
And don't get discouraged, okay? The
You're meant to
Correct. Correct.
Correct. Correct. Correct. Correct.
Correct. Correct. Okay? You should be
correcting constantly. You should be
detecting problems constantly. So, don't
get disturbed, all right? We said the
other night, and I'll say it again.
When you first start meditating, and you
finally learn to listen to the state of
your mind, it's a little disturbing.
How little you can concentrate. You see,
you you always were like that, but you
were never aware of it cuz
you never listened to it before. So,
don't think you're getting worse. You're
just detecting what you've always been.
All right. I I want to make two uh
pitches at this point, okay?
Ultimately speaking,
whether or not you can keep the mind on
the object, and whether or not you can
keep the mind fresh, has nothing to do
with your own conscious effort.
All right? Like he doesn't get into it,
but Geshe Kelsang does.
It's not up to your conscious effort.
Why? There are days when you want to
stay in the office and you can't.
And there are days when you'd like your
mind to be fresh, but it's not.
And you can tell your mind to be fresh,
but it's not going to be.
And you can tell your mind to stay in
the office, and it's not going to.
Because you don't really in the present
moment have any control over those
things. And that's a basic Buddhist
principle. You don't have control over
the current condition of your body and
mind. You can't tell your body not to
get breast cancer.
And you can't tell your mind not to be
depressed.
There will be days when it does, and you
can't stop it. Because those those
things are determined by earlier events,
uh that could Whether or not your body
develops
cancer cells, or whether or not your
mind is depressed at any given moment,
is all coming from something you did 6
months before.
And you don't have control over it in
the present moment. You can plan for 6
months from now.
But you you can't Ultimately, you can't
make your mind
be fresher, or hold the object. This
This is all sort of a
theoretical thing here.
This is saying, "Take the aspirin,
but be aware that it might not work."
You have to set up the causes ahead of
time. What are the causes for having a
great meditation?
Uh he said something something to that
effect, right?
Collect some good karma ahead of time.
Especially those of you going into
three-year retreat, right? It's very
cool to do some huge virtuous project
just before you go into a long retreat.
It gives you
uh power.
It gives you karmic seeds which will
continue to open during the three-year
retreat.
Uh you shouldn't be one of those people
who says they are meditator and has no
clue about the details of meditation,
right?
Uh you have to develop
uh meditation which has both of those
qualities, fixation on the object
and a freshness of mind, clarity, right?
Freshness of mind.
Uh which would include the ability to
tighten down on the
What do you call that?
The hole. Tighten down on the hole of
the object,
as you would a ball with the proper
amount of tension, right?
As I explained before, you have to be
able to tie your mind to the object as
if you were tying a rope to the object,
okay? You have to almost have the
physical sensation
as you begin in meditation of tying your
mind to the object of meditation.
Once you build it on the object,
then dullness and restlessness are going
to
You have to be able to detect when they
are about to ruin your hold on the
antidote.
He didn't say detect when they happen.
He said detect when they are about to
happen. Chuck chuck means about to
happen.
And
then instantly the watchdog mind has to
raise the alarm.
We're about to think about what?
Ding ding ding ding ding ding ding ding.
You know, okay?
That's what that's my idea. Okay, so so
and then
tell the thing and go. And then jump to
the appropriate antidote.
If you have dullness,
tighten down a bit.
If you're about to get distracted, what?
Listen to a bit.
It seems counterintuitive. You have to
You it's something you have to
experience. That's why we're doing the
January retreat, right? This is the
theory course.
January is the practical course. Or you
know,
your three-year retreat, all right?
Just slightly practical.
So, we'll
You'll get a chance in January.
We will sit down and
and we'll explore, you know, if if
listening up when you get
agitated in the mind helps or not. Okay?
We'll see.
Maybe we'll do little exercises, like
10-minute exercises. Okay, tighten up
when you're already distracted.
And we'll see what happens.
Like that. Let's do it.
This the purpose of the structure of
this 10-year teaching
is that we do
10 days of
theory, and then we go into the
laboratory and try all ourselves in a in
a deep meditation retreat without a cell
phone or
laptop.
We are going to do the great kindness
of taking away your electronics at the
door.
Okay? People charge a lot for that.
Canyon Ranch will charge you $1,000 a
day.
You know? All we do is give you a bunk
bed and charge you for that.
It's not a
Okay? For the honor of taking away your
electronics from
Okay.
Uh there are other teachers.
Once you get away from your dollars
and once you've overcome restlessness,
then
you will start to reach ekagrata. You
will start to reach
uh a single-pointedness of mind. I
struggled for a long time
with what does ekagrata mean? What does
single-pointed meditation mean?
And then uh my lama showed me a
scripture. It said,
"Single-pointed meditation." It said, "I
used to think of it was somehow my head
would get more like What are those guys
in the cartoon?
Uh
coneheads. Yeah, coneheads. I thought
maybe I'll get some kind of conehead or
something.
And then he said, "No, no. It refers to
a single object. Single-pointed
meditation
means uh meditation which has only one
object. All right? That's all."
You're meditating on your lama's form or
you're meditating on compassion or and
you or you're meditating on the eyes of
your heart teacher and that's all. The
only one object, okay?
That's ekagrata. Uh sel che
Sel che the ne. You will reach
single-pointedness.
Go ba.
Try to maintain an intensity of the
freshness of your mind, which again is
the feeling of being lost in the object,
okay?
Uh
Just think favorite song. Think favorite
music. That's true meditation.
It's not spaced out. It's a deep feeling
of enjoyment, right? It's uh it's being
engrossed
in the music. You feel lost in the
music. You're not aware of anything
else. It's all me and you.
You know? And you're just not thinking
about anything else. You're
deeply
pleasurably engrossed in your object.
Okay, that's that's all. It's like that.
Kissing your high school girlfriend.
You know? Now, I remember I was in the
driving.
That's why Arizona doesn't do uh
daylight savings time.
You don't know that?
No, they said it would ruin all the
driving movies.
Uh
no, I'm not kidding.
Probably they had the same experience as
I did, all those legislators.
Uh
I remember the guard at the driving
coming in banging on the window of the
station wagon with his flashlight, you
know?
And we both popped up.
And
the whole place was empty.
And there's no more movie. The movie's
been over for like an hour.
And uh
that's intensity.
And you're not thinking about anything.
You didn't hear 400 cars leaving.
You know?
Or you didn't notice that the the the
little box thing stopped beeping, you
know?
Okay.
I don't know what to say.
Uh
But it's like that. Something that
you're deeply That's That's real
meditation.
Making out with your high school
girlfriend.
That was a meditation. Seriously, the
state of mind was a meditator's. That's
what you want. It's excited, engaged,
it excludes other objects.
Okay. So, that's amazing.
Shishana. Chak Chen Tawa Ni.
This is beautiful. Then maybe we'll stop
in like 5 10 minutes, okay? Chak Chen
means what? Chak Chen Choku.
Mahamudra, right? So, Mahamudra has many
meanings. There's an asana called
Mahamudra asana.
There's a
There are many schools of thought in
India called Mahamudra.
Uh but in the study of meditation,
Mahamudra refers to choosing as the
object of your meditation your own mind,
okay?
Mahamudra is a is a lineage of
meditation which takes your own mind as
its object, all right?
Uh
Lekpa Don, Lekpa Zimbe Semni Nika, Kunga
Chene.
He says,
"Consider uh
Ma One of the great
beauties of choosing your own mind as
your meditation object, right? You can
choose your mind as a form.
Uh you can choose compassion.
But you can also watch your own mind and
explore its emptiness. You have to say
that, okay? Watching your mind is not an
innately deep meditation and it doesn't
help you.
It's not a It's not a innately powerful
object, right?
Uh
Watch your mind and explore its true
nature. That's Mahamudra. Watching your
mind is not Mahamudra, right?
Uh
Watching your mind
and trying to see where is it coming
from.
That's Mahamudra.
Uh
But anyway, when you are doing a
Mahamudra meditation, the object of the
mind is the mind itself, right?
Which has interesting implications on
the shishana.
On on being aware of whether your mind
is getting dull or restless,
the fact that you're watching your mind
already makes for an interesting
scenario. Okay?
Like the mind watching the mind gets
dull watching the mind get dull. Got it?
Uh and like that. So, into Mahamudra is
built almost uh
idiot-proof safeguards.
You're watching your mind is the object.
If you've lost the object,
uh
you don't have awareness of
of of whether your mind is lost it. You
see? It's very interesting. If you
detect dullness,
your mind is already dull.
It's kind of
uh one of the selling points for
Mahamudra meditation is that it's very
hard to get dull on the object.
Uh because if you're on the object, it's
not dull because you're watching your
own mind. Okay, got it?
Mhm. Mikpa don. So, mikpa mikpa's
difference and me. The object, which is
your mind, and the subject, which is the
mind watching the mind,
chick. They are the same mind.
These Zero means uh sheep herder.
Okay? Uh
ra look ra ra ra
ra look rila shawa. They are on the
on the what do you call a hill. They're
in the hills
watching to see if they have lost any
goats or sheep or not.
Right?
So, the
the sheep herder is watching for two
things. The sheep herder is checking two
things. What are they?
Are the sheep here
and are the sheep gone?
All right.
They're They're watching for two things,
really. How many sheep are missing? How
many sheep are here? Like, you can think
of it that way. All right. They are
looking what's here and what's not here
at the same time.
Mahamudra has that same flavor.
Then, this is interesting.
In the study of
in the practice of Mahamudra, in the
taking the mind as the object of
meditation, right?
What are you examining?
The nature of the mind.
Specifically, what is its ultimate
nature? Where has the mind come from?
You know, why am I perceiving depression
or why am I perceiving joy or, you know,
what are the causes of the fluctuations
of the mind?
Where do they come from? Which is karmic
seeds, right? So, your own mind is
examining each of the thoughts that
comes up in your mind to determine where
they came from, right?
So, if if dullness comes up in the mind
and you examine where it came from,
what's going to happen?
It's going to disappear.
Because that's an active state of mind.
If you examine where a state of mind has
come from, it's no longer thought.
So,
through Mahamudra meditation, where your
own mind is exploring your own mind's
nature, automatically avoids the
problems of meditating.
Because you can't examine the nature of
the mind and think about lunch.
And you can't examine the nature of the
mind and fall asleep because you're
active. The mind is active, right? It's
a very beautiful thing. And if you try
Mahamudra, you'll see that. It's much
easier
to reach a dogmatic single pointedness
in a Mahamudra meditation, then not a
meditation on your llamas form or
something like that.
Because the mind you are using to
explore the mind
is made fresh by the exploration.
So, if you think about it,
in a Mahamudra meditation, if your own
mind is the object of your meditation,
you have two options for stopping
problems.
You have two separate options for
stopping dullness or stopping
restlessness. Number one,
explore the nature Take that dullness as
the object of your mind.
Got it? Take that dullness as the object
of your meditation.
Don't try to stop it.
Just take the dullness. Say, "Oh, look,
dullness." Or "Oh, look, I'm thinking
about lunch. Now, why am I thinking
about lunch? What happened? What karmic
cause is there that I'm thinking about
lunch? What's the true nature of my
thinking about lunch?"
By examining the true nature of your
thinking about lunch, you have already
stopped thinking about lunch.
Okay? So, it's kind of Mahamudra is this
beautiful system.
Exploring the nature of your distraction
or exploring the nature of your dullness
removes it.
Or, he says, "Or, option number two, you
could just undertake the traditional
antidote. If you're dull,
uh think about how clear your mind is.
If you are restless, think about your
death."
For example, all right? And they will
bring your mind down or they will bring
your mind up. Got it?
So, for Mahamudra
Mahamudra,
you have two choices. You can examine
where the dullness is coming Take the
dullness as the object.
Take the agitation or the restlessness
of the mind as the object.
And explore its nature and that will
remove it.
Or you can apply that traditional
antidote that we talked about, okay?
If you want more detail on this, go to
the first Panchen Lama's classic text on
Mahamudra or his auto commentary, okay?
Uh similar in order to some proper
explanation.
Similar in meaning and then
similar in order also.
Those of you who wish to achieve
a deep state of meditation, should If
you are attracted to this object, you
have to go for the object that you're
attracted to, all right?
I I happen to really enjoy
picturing my lama.
You know, I could spend all day.
I could spend all day. I get trouble.
Uh
you know, I daydream all day
about my lama's form or what my lama
said or things like that. You can take
that as your object. Or you can
take emptiness. You could do emptiness
solving problems all day,
okay? Solving emptiness problems all
day? Like that.
Or you could Or you could focus on your
own mind
and watch your own mind and and think
about the nature of your mind. Where has
it come from?
Why am I experiencing this? Take the
meditation object which is naturally
attracted to you and go with it, okay?
Okay? Ride with it, all right? Take
Take I've given you a couple of options.
Mostly just think about whatever
spiritually uplifting thing you get
distracted by.
And and meditate on that. Take that as
your object. Take as your object
whatever you're attracted to.
I like my lama.
You might like your money. Or you can
focus on emptiness or you can focus on
both of them, you know?
You know, okay? Anything that you find
you find attractive.
You know, she may get a bigger shape or
something.
Some are there, some are not there. Some
are good,
some are not.
I'm going to push a little bit, okay?
You all right?
Yes.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah. No, no.
I'm going to be late but anyway, okay.
Uh
He's going to discuss the nine
stages of uh
the nine levels of meditation, okay?
Here we go.
You tell me. So, this is cool, okay?
Here's my selling point for
understanding the nine levels of
meditation.
Here's my selling point for
understanding the nine levels of
meditation.
Uh
I I like to school. I enjoyed high
school, for example,
because it was so clear where you were,
you know? I said, "You're in algebra
class.
You're in college prep
algebra class, period three with Mr.
you know, Mortensen or whatever it was,
you know? Like, I'm in class
period three. I'm in algebra. I'm I'm in
second level algebra.
And and I have to finish page 45 and 46
today and be ready for a quiz on it
tomorrow. Like, to me it was very
comforting
to know exactly where I was, you know?
You're you're You're a sophomore. You're
period three, you're sitting in that
class. And and we consider you a second
level algebra student.
And you have this teacher and you're
doing these pages today, okay?
Now, the problem with meditation is that
it's so What do you call that?
Nebulous.
It's so nebulous, right? Like, you have
no idea where you are sometimes. You
know, am I in good meditation or not?
You know, have I progressed in the last
two years or not?
You know, where where am I? Is there any
what do you call it?
Metrics. British Airways they excuse me.
I was thinking of our question about the
schedule. I'm like
what's the schedule?
We were sitting in this room on the
retreat and these two ladies were about
to go into meditation and they said how
long can we go for a week?
Excuse me?
And they said how long can we go for a
week?
I'm sorry I didn't catch that. And they
said can we go for a week?
And I'm like
I'm like maybe that's a pee pee.
And they said yes. And then I watched
them as soon as they did.
And they went to the bathroom, you know.
I was like yeah, it was a really
Why did I get so emotional?
Oh yeah, yeah, yeah.
And then they came back
and they said we need metrics, you know.
Like this is all very interesting but
how do you expect to prove that it
worked on the 43,000 employees of
British Airways?
Now what kind of how are you going to
measure the progress?
You know, it's like more people are
aware of comic series. I mean how do you
measure that?
And then I I'm like that's another
subject but if you have metrics
it it makes you feel happy. You say I'm
on I'm on stage four.
I've got my meditation at the stage
four. And you also have goals, right?
You say I'm going to try to get to stage
five by December.
First the end of the year retreat, you
know. You can say I'm shooting for a
level nine by you know September 3rd.
And then you can count the three breaths
by then and
So anyway
he gives us 11 levels of meditation,
which to me are very comfortable. They
are metrics
for meditation. How do you know that you
have gotten
that you're getting good? How do you
know what level you're on? Here we go.
Uh
Gom che ma den la sem ne
uh
sem ne la nyom tam pa gyur.
If you want to become a serious
meditator, you have to become familiar
with the mind levels of meditation.
The the defining
levels of progress, right?
Den la sem ne go she gyur. So, here are
the
nine levels of meditation.
They are sem gyopa. I'm going to give
you the translation I used on the
posters, so
so you don't get confused, okay? So, I I
wrote down the translations I used
15 years ago.
Sem gyopa is setting the mind on the
object. Number one.
Setting the mind on the object. That's
now level one.
Level number two. Gyune gyopa means
keeping the mind on the object with
brief continuity.
Keeping the mind on the object with
Number three. Len ne gyopa. Len Len
means a patch
uh that you put on a len ma gyap means
uh
if you tear your clothing and you put a
patch on it, that's what len ma. So,
it's called patch-like meditation,
right?
And I don't like that translation
because it makes it sound as if you are
only on the object briefly.
What it means is you only have patches
that you are off the object.
Okay? It doesn't mean patches of time
you're on object, it means slight
interview intervals when you are not on
the object. I translate it as
keeping the mind on the object with
patches where you lose the object, okay?
Mhm.
Nyer ma gyopa means maintaining the mind
tightly on the object. That's number
four.
Level number four is maintaining the
mind tightly on the object.
Level number five, torche chepa means
controlling the mind.
By the way, we'll go through what they
are, all right?
That's that's a long story. We have to
go through that, all right?
Shiwar chepa means quieting the mind,
number six.
Number shiwar chepa, completely quieting
the mind, number seven.
Saying chig tu chepa.
Keep chig tu
Saying
I didn't say saying chig tu chepa.
I said saying chig tu chepa.
But you can say saying chig tu chepa.
Uh
that means attaining single pointedness.
Ekagrata, meaning single pointedness.
Nyamar jopa means samapatti, right?
That's uh reaching deep meditation. You
can call it deep meditation. Literally,
it means balanced meditation. What does
that mean?
It should not be
Yeah, you're not falling into
restlessness and dullness, okay? But
we'll get to that.
It's not that easy.
Nyamar jopa degu le. We'll do We'll do
I'll go five more minutes. We'll do many
one or two, okay? Give the first one.
Nyamar le namar le medag ngag chig tu
chig tu chig chig.
You have been able to establish with
your teacher's guidance what you should
choose as your meditation object, all
right? With your teacher's guidance
you have been able to decide on a
meditation object, all right?
De yag mepa la shakta shakta le
shecha mi nepe gyun tu mi thupa de.
You are only like My teacher called it
angun ngag chig. Say angun ngag chig.
Angun ngag chig.
He used to call it
house fly mind, okay?
And I said, "What's that mean?" He said,
"You know, there's a pile of poop on the
ground.
A house fly, they land and then they go
over there and then they come back and
then they go there and then they come
back and then they go there and then
they come back.
They don't hang out there.
You know, like they seem restless.
They're always
Then he accused me of being a Anyway,
It means your mind touches the object
and then it flies away. You just
You just touch the object and then
you're off again, all right? That's
number one. Shaktam shaktam shane
Shaycher, for the most part, you are not
on the object and there's no continuity.
You don't have two nickels to rub
together.
Meaning, you don't have two moments of
on the object to rub together, okay?
Like you're on a on a on a like that,
okay?
Yermay chukpay. Deshe sema to chushe bay
tok ki.
Chok um
chok druk ki wang du shorwa.
Rikpay marme nampar shecha way nam
chunya. Deshe sema to chushe bay tok ki.
If you examine your mind
at this point in your meditation career,
uh chok druk ki wang du shorwa rikpay,
you will become aware of just how
what do you call it? Distracted your
mind really is.
Nangwa nampar shecha way nam chunya.
And you will start to think that you're
getting worse.
Okay?
You will, for the first time, be aware
of how bad your mind is.
And you'll think that your meditation is
making you worse than before. But it's
not, you're just aware of what's always
been there.
All right? You're just finally It's the
same when you first start trying to keep
your vows.
Like somebody says, uh "Do you agree to
keep a vow not to gossip?"
You say, "Yes, I agree not to gossip,
and then
if you really keep track of it,
suddenly you feel like you're gossiping
all the time and you can't stop.
You've been doing that all along.
You would just become aware of it.
So, he says don't be bummed out
if you What's a better word for bummed
out? It's
Don't be bummed out if you
if it feels like you're worse than you
when you before you started meditating.
It seems like your mind is more
distracted than when you started to
meditate.
You're just becoming aware of the state
of your mind.
Being mental among the so many. It's not
that you are more distracted person than
you used to be.
You
are just discovering how distracted your
mind always has been.
So, now that's the first level.
You're able to hit on the object
occasionally
or in first moments, okay?
Number two. What's level number two?
Keeping the mind on the object.
If you are able to maintain a slight
continuity of the concentration on the
object, okay? Like
it's not just moments on the object. The
fly lands and it sits for a couple of
seconds. Then it takes off again.
Then that is just an example.
If you have a rosary,
a mala,
and you are doing Om Mani Padme Hum,
okay? Om Mani Padme Hum, Om Mani Padme
Hum, Om Mani Padme Hum, Om Mani Padme
Hum, Om Mani How many
beads are 30%?
Huh?
108, okay. Why?
They figure 10% is lost already.
If you want to get 108 mantras, then say
108.
8% is a loss, okay. So,
he says, this is beautiful because you
got a metric here.
If you can do 108 Om Mani Padme Hum on
your rosary, that you can time it
someday, okay.
And time it. If you can stay on the
object for that long, which is what, 30
seconds or a minute? I don't know, you
check.
Uh, then you then you use level two.
You're at level two.
I I had a beautiful experience. I was uh
living in Dharamsala.
We used to go back and forth to Delhi to
bribe the officers to get our visas.
Uh
You give the money to travel agent. He
hands it to the officer under the table.
I don't know why under the table, cuz
everybody's watching.
But anyway,
uh then I was on my way back and I got
to this train with a connection called
Pathankot.
And uh all these Tibetan people were
there, like milling around and rushing
in and out of this room, waiting room.
And and I was with this British guy and
we were like, "What's going on, you
know?" And they said,
uh they said,
who was a senior tutor.
This was written by the junior tutor,
okay. Then then they were like, "Ling
Rinpoche's in there, you know, and you
can meet him."
We said, "Can we meet him?" They said,
"Yeah, you can meet him, but you've got
to have something to offer." We ran to
the market, we bought these cheap Indian
pancakes,
and we ran back, you know, and and we
said, "Can we go in and see him?" And
they said, "Yeah, go ahead." And we ran
in there. And and
what I remember most about Ling Wu Pao
Teh is that he was going like this all
the time. You know?
He was like this. He would talk to you
and he would be in mudras.
And he I like he forgot his mudras or
something.
So,
108, all right? For money and neighbors.
And then I don't know even somebody tell
me tell us tomorrow how long it is. I
don't know.
Say that five thousand five hundred
dollars.
Uh at this point, level number two,
uh you have gained you have somewhat
subdued your random thoughts.
Meaning dullness, grossness, etc.
And And other times they reassert
themselves.
So, the
Nyam Nyam is a difficult word to
translate. Nyam means
the feeling of being there, okay? The
feeling that you're at level number two
is that
that this your mind's distractiveness
takes a break once in a while.
All right?
You get a You get brief breaks from your
mind's own distractiveness, all right?
You're like slight
It's like the distractions are taking a
break once in a while.
That's all. Nothing more glorious than
that. Oh,
you know, my my dullness took a
two-minute break just then.
Now I'm back in my dullness, okay? Like
that, all right? It's very difficult to
translate.
These are my subtle people.
Uh
this particular level, and I believe the
previous one, but we'll get to that,
they have accomplished to a certain
powers.
that there are I think it's the sixth
power.
But
what helps you achieve the second level
is thinking about the object. Someone
makes considering the object.
Thinking about the object.
There are Okay, let's review where we
are. We got five
problems of meditation. We got eight
antidotes for them.
The process of applying those eight
antidotes to the five
problems will result in nine
levels that you move up to, okay? And I
think it's six powers of five. I don't
know what we're going to do.
You'll be a six You'll be applying six
powers to achieve
to go through those
nine levels. Then the last thing you got
to know is there's going to be four
modes of the mind. There will be four
modes of the mind. We'll talk about it.
All right, don't get worried.
Uh
You will spend most of your time at
level number two in either dullness or
restlessness. Most of the time you will
be either in dullness or restlessness.
Uh there will be very little time on the
object, okay? Nearly.
Uh so we call it the stage at which you
are
you are progressing
uh
only with
generally means concentrating the mind.
It's not at all a relaxed time in your
meditation career. It's a fight.
It's a Level one and level level two are
are constant struggle. It's a struggle.
You can say that.
The mode of the mind at level and level
two is a struggle.
You're You're like wildly fighting
against
dullness and restlessness and you pretty
much don't have any control over it.
It's a It's a struggle, right?
You're struggling to concentrate.
So, I'll ask you a question.
Do you think the periods on the object
are longer at this point or the periods
off the object?
Yeah. So, the level two
and level one, obviously, are
characterized
by more time off the object than on the
object, right?
If you want to keep score.
I'll do one more. I'll do three and then
we'll stop, okay?
Somebody
So, the third level is called
You can call it patches like meditation,
you know, with patches where you lose
the object, all
You are on the object.
You lose the object and you quickly sew
a patch.
What's it What do you do on a bicycle
tire?
Yeah.
You like glue a patch on. There's a rip.
There's a tear in the tire.
And you
You catch it and you patch it, okay? So,
that's what we're doing, okay?
You catch yourself fairly quickly off
the object.
And
you bring the mind back to the object
like a patch, right? all right? Then
they jump to summary. Later on my
younger younger younger younger younger
The only difference between three and
two
is that the periods that you are off the
object are
decreasing, okay? They are decreasing.
Then the um
they were talking to me two years ago.
This is a time when you are
strengthening your awareness
on the object. Awareness is the rope
that you tie to the object. So you are
strengthening the capacity of your mind
to hold the object, okay? I mean, yoga
in yoga you are strengthening muscles,
right?
But maybe you are strengthening
attention also.
And intention also. But
you know, in the practice of yoga you
strengthen muscles that you
maybe weren't even aware of.
I heard people talking about Allison's
class. First of all, they all said they
really loved it and had a really good
time.
And they rarely get a challenging class
that they really love.
And and they No, the people who do yoga
a lot, they
they don't get
yummy classes a lot. So they were having
a yummy class. And then they said and
she was And then they were talking about
all the muscles that Allison mentioned
and where are they and what do they do
and
did you feel that muscle in your pelvis
and what was it called anyway? And they
were
talking about all that but the the point
is in
yoga with a good teacher, you are
strengthening little tiny muscles and
big muscle groups that you didn't even
you were never aware of.
Right?
In meditation you are doing the same
thing,
you are strengthening muscles that you
were never aware of. You didn't even
have a name for them, right?
There's apparently some muscle around
your pelvis. They all forgot the name of
it. You don't have to repeat it
tomorrow.
They were telling me it's some pelvis
muscle and that's all tiny.
And I forget the name of it.
And and it made me think of meditation.
In meditation, you are strengthening all
these discrete little tiny mental
muscles.
And you will learn different names for
them. The different muscles in your mind
you will learn different names for them.
And then you will consciously do
exercises to strengthen each of them
until the whole body of the mind is a
strong.
Okay?
So,
level three, you are strengthening the
ability of the mind to
to hold on to the object, right? Which
is a very basic muscle
that you need, all right? Then there are
more subtle muscles that you will need,
all right?
And you have to exercise that muscle
in the mind.
So, those are the first three of the
nine levels. And we'll start at number
four tomorrow, okay?